Guide to the Weymouth Family Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Weymouth family papers
1891-1964
SC0478
Weymouth family.
Weymouth, Frank W. (Frank Walter), 1884-1963.
2.5 Linear feet
These papers include correspondence, lectures, articles, student essays, poetry, and short stories of Frank Weymouth, Alice Jenkins Weymouth, Oliver P. Jenkins, and others. Photographs and negatives in the collection include images of family members, beach scenes, crabbing activities in Anacosta, Washington, clamming in the San Francisco Bay area, and Mt. Rainier expeditions. Papers of Frank Weymouth include letters from his parents while he was a student at Stanford, 1906-1912; his letters to Alice Jenkins prior to their marriage; Stanford student memorabilia; pocket diary for 1905; lectures for comparative biology, 1934; professional correspondence with Donald C.G. MacKay, 1932-46, concerning their mutual interests in crabs, MacKay's work with Julian Huxley, and other matters; and letters from friends, 1905-63. Correspondents include Stanford classmate Ernest G. Preisker; and friends George Brammer and Elsa Dresbach, some of whose letters mention Kathleen Norris. Papers of Alice Jenkins Weymouth include compositions from English classes at Stanford, 1906-10, botany notes and drawings, 1904-05, and several letters. Papers of Oliver P. Jenkins include several commencement addresses, lecture notes on physiology, and a short story he wrote for his granddaughter.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
These papers largely pertain to Frank Weymouth, his first wife Alice Jenkins, and other members of the Jenkins family. Frank Weymouth was educated at Stanford University, earning his a.b. in zoology in 1909, his M.A. in physiology in 1911, and his doctorate in 1923. He joined the faculty of the physiology department in 1910, was appointed Professor in 1931, and served as head of the department from 1938-1949. At his retirement in 1949, he was appointed Professor Emeritus. He died in 1963. In 1912 he married Alice Mabel Jenkins, who earned her a.b. in physiology at Stanford in 1911. Her father, Oliver P. Jenkins, was a member of Stanford's first faculty and the first chairman of the physiology department. Alice Jenkins Weymouth died in 1933; in 1943 Frank Weymouth married Mary Balsbough Deirup.
Description of the Collection
These papers include correspondence, lectures, articles, student essays, poetry, and short stories of Frank Weymouth, Alice Jenkins Weymouth, Oliver P. Jenkins, and others. Photographs and negatives in the collection include images of family members, beach scenes, crabbing activities in Anacosta, Washington, clamming in the San Francisco Bay area, and Mt. Rainier expeditions.
Papers of Frank Weymouth include letters from his parents while he was a student at Stanford, 1906-1912; his letters to Alice Jenkins prior to their marriage; Stanford student memorabilia; pocket diary for 1905; lectures for comparative biology, 1934; professional correspondence with Donald C.G. MacKay, 1932-46, concerning their mutual interests in crabs, MacKay's work with Julian Huxley, and other matters; and letters from friends, 1905-63. Correspondents include Stanford classmate Ernest G. Preisker; and friends George Brammer and Elsa Dresbach, some of whose letters mention Kathleen Norris. Papers of Alice Jenkins Weymouth include compositions from English classes at Stanford, 1906-10, botany notes and drawings, 1904-05, and several letters. Papers of Oliver P. Jenkins include several commencement addresses, lecture notes on physiology, and a short story he wrote for his granddaughter.
Access Terms
Brammer, George.; Dresbach, Elsa, 1907-; Huxley, Julian, 1887-1975.; Jenkins, Oliver P., (Oliver Peebles), 1850-1935.; MacKay, Donald C. G.; Norris, Kathleen Thompson, 1880-1966; Preisker, Ernest G.; Weymouth family.; Weymouth, Alice Jenkins, 1883-1933.; Weymouth, Frank W. (Frank Walter), 1884-1963.; Anacosta (Wash.) --Photographs.; Clams --California --San Francisco Bay.; Lectures.; Photoprints.; Rainier, Mount (Wash.) --Photographs.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Correspondence: Frank Weymouth to Alice Jenkins, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Frank Weymouth to Alice Jenkins, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: John and Melissa Weymouth to Alice Jenkins, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Frank Weymouth from his parents, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Frank Weymouth from his parents, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Frank Weymouth from his parents, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Frank Weymouth from his parents, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Frank Weymouth from his parents, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Frank Weymouth from his parents, January - May, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Frank Weymouth from his parents, June - September, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Frank Weymouth from his parents, October - December, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Frank Weymouth from his parents, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Frank Weymouth from his mother, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence to Alice and to Frank Weymouth (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Frank Weymouth from friends, 1905-1908 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Frank Weymouth from friends, 1908-1912 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Frank Weymouth from friends, 1924-1952 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence "B-C": Frank and Mary Weymouth from friends, 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence "D": Frank and Mary Weymouth from friends, 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence "I-W": Frank and Mary Weymouth from friends, 1956-1962 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Alaskan Glacier Sea Food Co. -
    - Correspondence with Frank Weymouth re Alaskan Crab Fishery. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Anderson, Malcolm Playfair -
    - Letter from MPA; offprint of biographical article by Anderson's father (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Book Inventory
    - Letter from MPA; offprint of biographical article by Anderson's father (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - California Optometric Assc. Remarks (1964) -
    - Typescript of remarks by Anne Weymouth Deirup before COA convention (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Citizenship Lectures
    - Typescripts of lectures on evolution by Profs. Jordan & Brown, October 9, 10, & 23, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - DAR Palo Alto Chapter, Blacklist Affair -
    - Papers re. protest & resignations over speakers' blacklist (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - DAR Palo Alto Chapter Clippings re Blacklist affair (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - DAR Palo Alto Chapter Memorial Tribute to JH Gilbert -
    - Typed tribute to JH Gilbert by ER Jenkins; clippings; etc. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Duffus, Robert -
    - Letter to Mrs. Storm 1944, letter from Frank Weymouth 1945 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Edible Clams, Mussels & Scallops of CA -
    - Published study by Frank Weymouth (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Foss, John E. -
    - Correspondence with John W. and Frank W. Weymouth; letters, poetry (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Hester Family Memoirs -
    - Two memorial accounts by ancestors of E.R. Hester Jenkins (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Jenkins, Alice. Stanford Compositions, English 8, 1906-1907 (1) -
    - Biographical essay & firsthand account of 1906 earthquake; description of Cedro Cottage (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Jenkins, Alice. Stanford Compositions, English 8, 1907 (2) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Jenkins, Alice. Stanford Compositions, English 21, 1909 (3) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Jenkins, Alice. Stanford Compositions Misc., 1910 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Jenkins, Alice. Botany 1 -
    - Sketchbook of botanical pencil drawings & notes, 1904-1905 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Jenkins, Alice. Letters, 1891, to maternal grandfather and father (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Jenkins, Elizabeth Hester; Memorial Testaments, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Jenkins, Hubert O. -
    - Research notes & publications on Field Mice (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Jenkins, O.P.: Commencement Address, 1910 -
    - Typescript of commencement address delivered at the University of the Pacific (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Jenkins, O.P. Commencement Address, 1897 -
    - Typescript of commencement address delivered at Cooper Medical (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Jenkins, O.P. "Our Educational System, Its Cause and Its Cure" (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Jenkins, O.P. Pencil Sketches, 1890s (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Jenkins, O.P. Physiology 155 lecture notes (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Jenkins, O.P. "What Happened to Isis" -
    - Story written for his granddaughter, Anne Weymouth, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Jordan, David Starr. List of Publications, 1873-1903 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Little Nonsense, Vol. 1, no 3, October 1896 -
    - Branner family publication (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - MacKay, Donald C. G. -
    - Correspondence with Frank Weymouth, 1932-46 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Madrono, 1901-1902 (includes stories by Hubert Jenkins) (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Miscellany (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - The Palo Alto Tree (Publication Contract) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - The Shooting Star, number 13 (Jan. 1897) - 20 (May 1899) -
    - Composed and printed by Alice, Hubert & Olaf Jenkins (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Smithsonian Institution Academy of Sciences -
    - Correspondence with Frank Weymouth re article submissions (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "The Soft Shell Crab" -
    - Musical score with lyrics (by Frank Weymouth?). (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Stanford, Leland and Jane - reproduction of 1850 daguerreotype. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Sterling, J.E. Wallace -
    - "Memorial Resolution" re Frank Weymouth (copy) (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Student Matters -
    - Correspondence from and re students: David Nicol, Al L. Nicholson (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Student Phorcaster 10:2 (December 1956) -
    - Los Angeles College of Optometry student publication; contains article on Frank Weymouth (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Tompkins, Clara -
    - Tribute to; letter: J. Tomkins to A. Weymouth 1930 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Weymouth, Frank. Comparative Biology Notes, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Weymouth, Frank. Misc. Writings, 1908-1912 -
    - Poems, "Description of a new Corystoid Crab from the Kerocene of Palo Alto" (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Weymouth, Frank. Pocket Diary (1905) (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Weymouth, Frank. Stanford U. Misc. Communications, 1907-1909 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Weymouth, Frank. Statistical Inference notes (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Photographs:
    - Ocean Views and Sand Dunes (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Near Auburn, WA, August 12, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Photos from around SF Bay Area, Jan + Feb 1911 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Frank Weymouth in Swanton ,CA Jan 1911 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - In Eureka,CA and Trinidad Head, CA March 1911 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Anacosta, WA, August 1911, Crabs and Crabbing (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Anacosta, WA August 1911, Crabs and Crabbing (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - SF, Bayside, Clam Digging (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Photos not in Series from Mt Ranier and Mt Desolate expedition, July, August 1913 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Alice and Frank Weymouth 7/30/13 - 8/1/13 Near Mystic Lake (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Mt Ranier Locations July and Aug. 1913, Series A (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Mt Ranier Locations July and Aug. 1913, Series B+ C1 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Mt Desolate Locations, Series C, [C1 in B] (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Mt Ranier Locations July and Aug. 1913, Series D Moraine Park: Olaf and Frank Weymouth worked together (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Frank Weymouth, Mt Expedition photos, Series E, Moraine Park (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Mt Washington and Northern Peaks; Frank Weymouth Photos (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Misc Photos, Frank Weymouth, Big Basin, CA, coast etc. Birds c. 1910 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Weymouth Family Beach Pictures 1917-1919 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Baby Pictures: Weymouth, Anne A. (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Baby Pictures: Weymouth, John 1924-1926 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Baby Nancy? (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Baby Pictures: Weymouth, Alice [daughter to Alice Jenkins] (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Photos: Alice Jenkins Weymouth, 12 mos, and college years (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Weymouth Children Photos, Alice, John + Anne; Easter egg hunts, Halloween, Tea Parties, etc. 1919-1924 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Portrait: Frank W. Weymouth c. 1911 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Photos: Unidentified Groups of People (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Misc Locations: Woods Hole, Room Interior (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - 1929? Photos from John E Foss to J.W. and Frank W. Weymouth, misc locations; view from hill, behind barn, [from box 2, folder 8] (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Photos of Mongol Women refered to in letter in Box 1, folder 22 from Malcolm Playfair Anderson to Mrs. Jenkins, c. 1908 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Portrait of Lt .AL Nicholoson ca. 1943, Student of Frank W Weymouth, from Box 3, folder 21 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Photos of the play at Theodore Hoover Ranch--Alice's Indian Play, June 1928 "El Proseta" and copy of newspaper account (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Photos-Cedro College (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Photos-Cedro College (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Photos- Children's Operetta, June 1926 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Earthquake Damage at Stanford U. 1906--photos (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Photographs--House at 3 Salvatierra, 1917-1923 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Stanford Scenes—photos (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Album of Stanford images pre 1906; includes the Stanford Family Statue in the Inner Quad, Memorial Church just prior to completion, and the Palo Alto Tree (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Book--The Innocents at Cedro (Inscribed by author R.L Duffus to Frank Weymouth) (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Photographic negatives (Box 5)